[Music]
Hey,
hey,
hey.
[Music]
Heat. Heat.
Hello, good evening, good day everybody
and welcome Welcome to the Ask Kavaj
Show. I hope everyone's doing great.
Today is a history episode. We're going
to discuss history. I've taken a bunch
of questions that you all have asked in
the comments and we'll take as many
questions as possible over the next
couple of hours. But before that, as
always, let us see who all is there on
the live chat with us. I can see it
space
jay bonjour, Swami J, A N A N A N A N A
N A N A N A N A N A Nisha Mishra Vishal
Nata, Yrad Singh, Shik Kawat, Shashank
Koshik. Good evening Aloc Bat Samant
from Odisha Rasputin Latangi Suresh
Latangi Suresh I am connected from
Tutamil I'm not really sure about that
but okay the world teacher Jagat Guru
Swami Viveandanda
U Valarandanda okay mystic skyri Krishna
Hya Shanks Mojour Dave HB Rashmi Raturi
Sud Ary Kash Anup Tik Anak Jin Dr. Surya
Kant Tagar, Suraj Kulkarni,
uh Vladimir Putin is there, Ram Shukla
from Kpur, Kpur, Vidi Manar, Jay Gumman,
uh GK, uh Chintapali, Kanaka, Mahesh,
Chetan, Aradyas, Sharma, Dark Knight,
good morning, Rasputin, VS, Na,
Rashmi, Ratar once again, Diddi's son is
here, Deb is here, Sat Gupta, Shankit,
Pad, Mitesh, Gandhi,
Vikash X an Aush Singh Raja Akash Kumar
Ujiha YT Duv Durya Rasputin PJ Jwal
Ketan Desai Beneath Might is Right
Creative Clips Random Skull Hello Nishad
Atalia Umesh Ush
uh Satellite
VS Nay Mitesh Gandhi once again okay I
think I'm repeating some Ragav Chopra
Suman Shakar Sarangi Deatra Das from
from X Rakav Chopra Swami Jin from
Jaipur Hideki Ryuga Tanmahesh Pandi
Vashish Sharma when will I do a Hindi
video in Hindi I'll see about that sir
I'll see Air Shukla from the city of
lakes Bopal good evening sir Vik Vishal
Tokas
might is right says take my name uh
Nalind geopolitical from Indor good
evening sir Rajat Duhan
Kish WHMA Jio is investing in AI models
that's fantastic Krishna Aruna from the
Surinamese Netherlands and so many other
people. Good evening, good day to all of
you. Thank you so much for being on the
live chat and let's get going with the
questions. I have taken some questions
20 25 questions. Let's get going with
the questions. What what are what all
are we discussing today? Okay, what's
the first question? Considering the role
of France France in the American
Revolution, could the colonies have won
their on their own? Could the could the
colonies the 13 colonies could have
could they have won on their own? How
much did the global balance of power
decide the outcome of this pivotal
moment? Okay, we're talking about the
American Revolution, the American War of
Independence, right? The Americans were
under British occupation. Well, they
were British. The Americans were
British. They were British colonizers.
What is the United States? It's an
artificial nation created by settler
colonialists. settler. It it was created
by created by settler colonization. A
bunch of Europeans came and discovered
this land for themselves starting from
the Vikings. But that that that was a
chapter that was forgotten from history.
And then you have uh Christopher
Columbus who set out to discover India,
set out looking for India. They stumbled
into the Caribbean region and then the
Spaniards discovered America and the
French and then the British and so on
and then there was a tussle between them
and the British came out on top and they
created the 13 colonies. The 13 colonies
they created and then they decided we
will no longer pay the 2% tax to the
king of England. We shall no longer pay
the tax. We shall keep all the money for
ourselves. And that's was that was the
revolt. That was the revolt that we no
longer want to pay any tax across the
Atlantic Ocean. We're going to keep all
the money here. This is our land now.
Okay. So that was the revolt. That was
the revolution. And uh that's what they
call the American war of independence
1765 to 1780 something 83 I think. Okay.
So what was the French role rule in
this? The French had a significant role.
You know the Americans today make fun of
the French. They call the French all
kinds of unflattering names, surrender
monkeys and whatn not. They keep poking
fun at the French. Without the French,
the Americans would not have won their
war of independence. Okay, I assure you
of that. So the French, they had this
longstanding
rivalry with the with the English. Okay,
if you go go to the beginning of the
20th century, it was a thousand years of
rivalry and enmity between France and
England in a and it it manifested itself
in so many different ways over the years
and the centuries.
So during this American revolution, the
French provided essential support to the
13 colonies uh military support,
financial support, diplomatic support,
all of that matters. Without military
support, without arms, ammunition,
material, material, you can't win a war.
Without financial support, we can't win
a war. And of course, when there's a war
ongoing, there's a there's a revolt
that's going on, you need somebody to
look out for you diplomatically.
France did all of that. So, the American
colonies would have faced tremendous
difficulty. They essentially would have
lost if it was not for the French and
the help that they provided. So I
remember when I was a kid like when I
was like 8 n maybe 10 years old I
watched this movie an American movie
about the deafet who was a French uh
military leader who participated in the
uh American revolution the war of
independence u and so the Americans did
recognize in the 20th century the the
French contribution to this. So what
kind of specific help did the French
provide? They provided first of all
troops and officers, French soldiers,
French commanders like I said the la
then there were some other people as
well the grass and and uh some other
names that I don't remember right now.
So
the grass and there were some other
major commanders and and soldiers as
well. lots of soldiers that were
provided by the French and these French
military commanders, these French
soldiers, they did
they did shape the the course, the
outcome of battles,
the final siege of Yorktown. Okay, what
was it? 80 1781 or something like that.
Okay, you can look up the exact dates.
The siege of Yorktown, who surrendered
in the siege of York Yorktown?
Lord Cornwallis
surrendered to the Americans and that
was essentially the beginning of the end
of the u the the rule of the British
flag in America. Lord Cornwallis who
later came and occupied India that
fellow. So the French provided soldiers
they provided military commanders they
they then they uh assisted the Americans
with naval power. the French Navy, it
engaged British forces not just in the
Americas but but globally. They blocked
British reinforcements at Yorktown u and
that that that essentially was crucial
to the victory of the Americans. This
diplomatic alliance also uh that the the
diplomatic support that the French gave
it gave legitimacy to the the to the
cause of the Americans and so on. So the
the American colonies they were
essentially like islands at that time.
America was still not genocided
completely. The natives still existed
and the colonies were like islands and
they lacked resources for a prolonged
war.
And the British side they had
reinforcement. They had supplies coming
in from across the Atlantic from from
Europe from continental Europe from from
England from Britain. So the French
provided this vital uh support to the
rebels, French supplies, French money,
French commanders, French soldiers.
Okay. And the French intervention forced
Britain to fight globally. Globally and
that's what really hampered Britain. And
that's when when this happens, when you
to fight not just in one place where the
rebellion is happening, but globally in
so many different places, you get
overstretched, your resources get
overstretched, your military gets
overstretched, your navy gets
overstretched, and you can't focus where
you're supposed to focus. And that's
what the French did. So without French
support, the US re the American
Revolution, the war of independence
would have failed. It's the French who
were instrumental in creating the United
States of America. Let's not forget
that. So it's it's it's a very
interesting question that you've asked
here and the world should know about
this. Yes. All right.
Vidhi manar says can you please uh tell
us about Sharda Petit one of our
greatest ancient centers of education
and learning now located in temporarily
Pakistan illegally occupied Kashmir. Who
was responsible for its decline and
eventual destruction? Who destroyed it?
What was the temple and university like
at the peak? at its peak what kind of
knowledge was imparted there what were
the qualifications of the scholars and
teachers associated with it are there
any books there where we can get all the
possible clear details of Sharda Petit
and so on look I am not aware of any
books I don't think anyone anyone has
bothered to write a detailed book about
Shardat and so on you know our
historians they are engaged in all kinds
of activities that have nothing to do
with Indian history
so I don't know of any books about
Shardet I have read from various
different sources I don't even remember
the sources I can go and look them up
again. Uh there are obviously research
papers and and fragments of of knowledge
and information from various books here
and there. But the books aren't about
Shardet. Right? So Shardet was one of
our great ancient universities. It
existed at least in the 4th century AD
probably before that. It is said to have
been created by Lord Vishnu or Lord
Brahma. one of the two I think one of
the two I don't remember exactly which
one so that indicates that it was
considered to be a very ancient
university uh I'm not sure exactly when
it was when it was founded and who
founded it but it was there at least in
the 4th century AD most likely must have
been there long before that
was obviously in Kashmir and uh because
of the presence of this great university
Kashmir The land of Rishikashap was also
known as Sharda. Sharda is obviously
uh Saraswati the goddess Saraswati the
goddess of of knowledge and wisdom and
some of the major patrons of this great
university were the great king Lalita
and his successors. So that's around the
7th 8th century is AD 8 9 10 11th
century AD around that time was the peak
of this university the peak I mean the
greatest extent and the peak of its fame
the peak of its attraction for students
all across the subcontinent maybe beyond
that right you would have scholars
coming in from what is currently the
Chinese occupied Singinjang etc that was
an completely Indianized region you had
uh scholars like Kumar Ajiva etc who
were associated with the university It
is said that Jagat Guru Shankrara was
also associated with the university. So
uh in ancient India the universities
were always uh patronized by kings. The
kings were patrons who would subsidize
the universities who who would give all
the money all the resources needed for
the upkeep and running of the
university. Sometimes expansion of the
university to provide for everything the
teachers and students and everybody
needs administrators all of that. So
that there is no obstacle in the smooth
running of the university and the
university uh is said to have had a
great library. We know that what
happened in Naranda right? Shardet also
had a great library. God knows how many
texts were there and the Sharda script
comes emerged out of well the Shara
Sharda University most like most likely
uh the Sharda script is associated with
Sanskrit and so with with it is
associated with Kashmir and Kashmir was
Shard.
So most likely Sharda University must
have been the place the institution from
which this this script emerged and the
Sharda script was used for writing
Sanskrit as well as local languages like
uh the precursor to modern day Sanskrit
and the various other Daradic languages
that uh were spoken in the northwest
northern and western parts of India.
We're talking about extreme northwest
which is Kashmir and Gandhar and so on.
So uh it was a great university. It was
a great institution of wisdom,
knowledge. What did they teach there?
They taught you everything that was
taught in all Indian universities. They
would teach you philosophy. They would
teach you the shastras. They would teach
you the itas. They would teach you
mathematics. They would teach you
astronomy. They would teach you the 64
vidyas, the 64 arts, all of that.
Everything you were taught in Nalanda or
Takashila or Telhara or Vikramila or or
Odantaapuri or Walabi or whatever.
Everything all of the same things were
also taught in Sharda University. We
don't have any records of its curriculum
of its syllabus. Nothing is left today.
Everything has been burnt into ashes. So
we don't know quite what the details
are.
But the ancient Indian universities all
taught similar subjects. Everything
there were vishua vidyalas everything
under the sun would be taught there. And
you would obviously have great scholars
there. Qualifications and all. Well, we
don't have records. We don't have a
single name today that still exists of
someone who taught there.
Right? We know that Jagat Guru Shankrari
was associated with it. We know that uh
uh Kumar G was the great the great
central Asian scholar of Indian and
Kashmir ancestry. He was also associated
with the with the Shardit. But we don't
know the details of what they taught,
what were the what was the curriculum
like? What texts they may have used and
so on. All of that is been wiped out and
we don't know
uh any books. I I don't I'm not aware of
any books. So, I'm sorry I can't help
you with that. But maybe if we look
around and if we do some deep research
digging for information, maybe we can we
could perhaps find something. But as of
right now, I don't know of any books.
So, that's what I can tell you in in in
brief. And if you're really interested,
I all all of you my viewers, please go
ahead and and do some investigation on
your own. And if you can find something
of interest, something interesting, some
some new valuable information, please do
share it. All right, next question.
This is by Uraj Singh Shikawat.
What does the presence of Indis Valley
seals in Mesopotamia signify?
So what are these Indis Valley seals?
Did they come from the Indis Valley,
Zindu Valley? Well, no. They came from
Indian civilization which at that time
was kind of well the area of focus that
we talk about is the Satasindu region.
The seven regions which is Punjab
the six the five Punjab means five
rivers right but there was also the
Saraswati which no longer exists today
except in the northern part of India. So
you had this great saraspati synindu or
satasindu civilization satasindu era of
our history of Indian civilization and
that region was well highly highly
developed highly industrialized fully
urbanized complete standardization of
weights and measures and so on. It was
extremely prosperous and extremely
influential and our ancestors from that
time who lived in that region they
traded with the rest of the world with
the rest of the civilized world and what
was right west of India we had
Mesopotamia
so if you look at the map
if we look at the where's the map let's
find the map okay is map let us put map
on screen let us put the map on the
screen So
all right okay here we are so this is
the map we're talking about uh you know
we're talking about what what part of
the subcontinent are we talking about
we're talking about Gujarat northern
Maharashtra parts of M of MP we're
talking about Rajasthan Hana Punjab
Jammu Kashmir we're talking about the
whole of Pakistan present day Pakistan
we're talking about Balojasthan we're
talking about Gandhar Afghanistan
um and all the way up to the up to parts
of Tajakistan and also eastern Iran. So
all of that was part of the Saraswati
Hindu uh
so to say civilization
that part of our civilizational history.
And to the west we obviously had Persia
and to west of the west of Persia you
had the great uh uh kingdoms and and
empires that existed in Mesopotamia.
And at that time we had trading posts in
the Gulf region. Uh where was it? Was it
Oman? Somewhere in Oman? I suppose we
also had trading posts in in in very in
far northern India and we also had
connections with the Girroth
civilization
which was a sis which was kind of a
sister or daughter civilization that
existed in eastern Iran. So if you go
west of India, you reach Iran and in
Iran we had gi
culture or girroth civilization and that
was kind of the bridge between India and
Mesopotamia. So our traders would
essentially sail westwards cross the
straight of Hormuz and they would
essentially reach this region and from
here they would trade with the
Mesopotamians
and there is a ample evidence of trade
between India and Mesopotamia.
Mesopotamia and cultural connections and
trade connections. Uh we find that u
some Mesopotamian kings were given red
Indian dogs as gifts. You know the wild
dog that you have in India, the duel,
not the standard dog that you have on
the streets of India, but there's
another subspecies of dog called the
duel. It's a reddish brown dog and it is
not tamed dog. It's not a domesticated
dog. It's a wild dog. So that dog was
given to one of the Mesopotamian kings
and uh there there's I think langours
were presented as gifts because langors
only occur in the Indian subcontinent
and of course you have the presence of
all these uh in these seals in
Mesopotamia. You find a wide variety of
Indian seals in the Mesopotamia region.
Uh so what does it signify? It it
signifies trade. Maybe the tra the seals
were the stamps of various trading
houses of various corporations, right?
It's it's possible. Uh so so that sort
of thing. So each seal has some kind of
motif. Maybe it is uh the master of
beast beasts motif. Maybe it is a
pashupati motif. It is maybe it's a
bull. Maybe it is whatever it is, right?
Lots of bulls. You would have lots of
inscriptions of rdra and so on. And
these probably were the the trading
seals or or the or or the logos you
could say of various Indian corporations
would trade. So the presence of Indian
seals in this region it indicates it
signifies the extensive trading contacts
we had with this region. That's what it
signifies.
Okay.
Yajj Navalia says the Akamerid Empire at
its greatest extent was larger in area
than the Roman Empire at its greatest
extent. Given that the various Persian
empires ruled over the whole of Western
Asia for about a millennium or even
more, what can we say about their impact
on West Asian cultures? Excellent
question.
So yes, the Persian Empire, the
Hakamanish or Kamanish Empire uh it uh
conquered, let's once again go to the
map, it conquered various I mean the
whole whole of what we call the Middle
East or West Asia today. So it starts
from the borders of India. There is the
borders present borders of Afghanistan
and Pakistan. And you go and you go
westwards you have Persia and they
conquered well essentially everything.
They conquered all the way to Anatolia
uh present day Iraq, Syria, the whole of
Mesopotamia, most of Arabia I suppose
and also Egypt. Egypt was also uh a
vasal and uh of of the Akameid Empire of
the Persian Empire and also in the
Caucasus region you had their presence.
So and overall it was a vast empire the
Persian Empire uh you rightly say it was
it was larger in extent in geographical
extent than uh the Roman Empire at its
greatest extent. That's how large the
aimed Empire of Persia was. It was a
very vigorous geopolitically vigorous
empire, an expansionist empire, always
expanding westwards, westwards,
westwards and they fought the Romans
eventually, right? And they had pretty
good success against the Romans as well.
So that's was the deal of the uh Persian
Empire, the Aimeirate Empire. So
obviously they're going to have some
cultural influence. they would have had
a great amount of cultural influence and
impact over uh over West Asia. But that
has all been erased.
Today you don't see that. You see some
remnants of that here and there. For
example, in in Persia, in Iran today,
you still have some small scattered
Jewish communities, small numbers of
Jews here and there. How did the Jews
end up in Persia? Well, the the the
Persians, they they liberated
the the Jews from what was it? As a
Assyrian occupation
and they all they they allowed the Jews
to re to retake the Jerusalem and build
the second temple there, which was
eventually destroyed by the Romans.
Okay? And that's a whole different
story. And as a consequence, the Jews
who were in exile were able to go back
to Judea
to present day Israel. And some Jews
eventually ended up in in Persia because
Persia was a very well welcoming
civilization just like we used to be
just like we still are. The Persians are
also just like us. So Jews were were
welcomed in Persia and some of them
settled down in various parts of Persia
and they also continued practicing their
religion. Uh so the Persian Empire was a
very
the western term is tolerant,
religiously tolerant. They were
obviously eventually they became
Zoroastrians but they allowed all their
conquered peoples to continue practicing
whatever cultures and religions they
had. So it was a very from a western
perspective tolerant
uh empire. The ra the more appropriate
term would be respectful of other
people's cultures. Not tolerant but
respectful. But that's something the
west doesn't understand. They don't
understand respectful. They understand
tolerant. I'm going to tolerate you.
That sort of thing. So anyway the
Persian culture would have spread far
and wide across West Asia but all of it
was wiped out eventually by the u by the
rise and spread of the religion of that
came out of Arabia right in the which
sixth 7th century AD whatever Islam I'm
talking about right and there's nothing
left of whatever uh cultural or
civilizational impact Persia would have
had on West Asia nothing that I can see
yeah so all of that was wiped out and of
because Persia was destroyed by
Alexander. So all the Persian records of
what they what they did, what they
achieved and all of that that also was
destroyed by Alexander. So there's
nothing much left that that can tell us
about the specific set of impacts Persia
would have had on West Asia also Egypt.
Amisha says,
"How was Pushia Pushia Shunga able to
execute the last Morian empire in
public?" Brihadrita Moria, right? That
was the last per last Morian emperor.
So, Pushamatraunga his justification was
that this guy the last Morian emperor
was absolutely
uh he was incapable of ruling. Okay. He
was uh he he had no qualities as a ruler
and he was running the empire into the
ground and the foreigners were
you know wreaking havoc in India. The
yaners and whatnot. So it's better that
somebody else takes over and and you
know gets a grip on on the empire and
and safeguards India from all this
nonsense. That was the the justification
and push mutra shunga. So the question
is how did he do this? So first of all
let's understand this. He did not
execute
the last Moria Empire. He assassinated
the last Morian empire emperor. It was
not an execution. It was an
assassination. Let me explain what an
assassination is.
You want to know about a public
assassination? Well, okay, I'll show
you.
Okay, let's Google this. Okay, we go to
alami
alami uh sad
assassination.
Okay, sad. Sadat, right? Okay, let's go
to images.
Okay, check this out. This is public. Do
you see what's happening here?
Uh,
look look what's happening here. This is
all public. You can see over here
there's a whole this is a stadium and
you can see people are sitting in in a
large number of people are sitting in
their seats. You can see over here this
is a zoomin kind of thing. You can see
some more details here. This is all in
public. So Anoir al-Sadat the leader of
Egypt was reviewing a military parade a
victory parade of of the Egyptian
military's achievements in the what Yom
Kipur war war. And there's a military
parade going on and uh one of the
vehicles stops in front of Sadat and
Sadat is standing and saluting them
because that's what you do right as as a
president you salute your armed forces.
So these and a bunch of people, a bunch
of soldiers comes out and they throw a
bunch of like three grenades at him and
one of the grenades explodes and then
the remaining soldiers they start
shooting at the president and you can
see over here people are throwing chairs
on the president so that he will be
shielded from the bullets. So that's
what happened in public. This was not a
public execution. This was a public
assassination.
As you can see here, there's very few
images available of uh of the Anar
Al-Sadat assassination. But here you
have a few. This happened what in ' 61
it was in sorry it was in 1981
Anoir Al-Sadat. So that's a more recent
example. So what happened between Pushia
Muttrashunga and Brihadrata Moria?
Pushya Mitraunga was the sapati
of the Moria Empire. He was the
commanderin-chief of the military of the
army of the Indian army. Okay. And the
Indian emperor was incompetent.
He was not fit to rule and it was
causing tremendous havoc and problems in
India. So the synapathy decided it's
time. So during a military parade
when all the soldiers are standing in in
formation with all their weapons
gleaming and the emperor comes and in
inspects them that's when the sapati
assassinated the emperor. It happened
during a military parade not in public
with all the Indian you know like
republic day or something. No it was a
military parade. That's where he was
able to assassinate the emperor, the
last emperor of the Morian Empire. And
obviously he had the full backing of his
army otherwise he would have been also
executed. Right? If he if his actions
did not have the full backing of the
military then Push Pushy Mitraunga would
not become the next emperor of India.
But he became the next emperor of India.
But his entire life he never called
himself Maharaji
which is emperor. He called himself
synapati. So he always said that I am
still the sapati. I am not an emperor.
But his descendants were obviously the
emp emperors after him. So that is how
it went.
Shah
shahasara
shah shahara shahasara. Okay. Says, "In
what time period of history did the Dasa
Raj Rajan Yuda or the battle of the 10
kings happen? Were the Yamna invaders of
Europe also expelled from India after
losing the war or was that event from a
different time frame?" Okay,
this is well in historical circles this
is controversial. Okay, so first of all
let's talk about the Yamna. The Yamna
invaders who rampaged across Europe and
in like few years it completely
transformed they conducted a proper
genocide of the Europeans of the male
Europeans and today's Europeans are
descendants of the Yamna males and the
females of that time of Europe. So the
Yamna
they suddenly emerged from somewhere in
the east about 4 and a half thousand
years before today. That is about around
2,500 BC around that time. That's when
this bunch of horse riders appear from
the east maybe from the Pontic Caspian
state maybe somewhere else. We don't
quite know from where they came but in a
short period of time historically short
period of time they completely
transformed Europe completely
uh
invaded occupied and settled the whole
of Europe all of it. That is 4,500 years
before today. It's it's known. We know
all the I mean there's ample
archaeological evidence of an invasion
of an Arian invasion of Europe. Okay.
um there's this mass graves and with
with horrific injuries on the skeletons
and also the genetics change in Europe
around that time 4,500 years before
today. So it's very clear this invasion
happened around 4 and a half thousand
years before today around 2,500 BC.
That's the Yamna invasion of Europe.
Those people they did not call
themselves Yamna. The Yamna means a pit
a pit in Russian. That's what it means.
It doesn't mean they those people call
themselves Yamna. Oh my name is Yamna.
We are the Yamna people. Oh, we have no
idea what they called themselves.
Now, so that is about the Yamya. That
sets the context. Now, what about the
battle of the 10 kings? Now, let me give
you an outstanding example of how
Wikipedia lies to you. Okay, we're going
to go to Wikipedia. And here I'm going
to show you in real time how Wikipedia
distorts history.
Look, uh Wikipedia,
Battle of 10 Kings, India.
I mean there's only one battle of 10
kings. Even if I remove India, it'll say
battle of 10 kings. Okay. So battle of
the 10 kings. It's going to tell you
exactly when it happened. Okay.
According to Wikipedia, this took place
between when did it happen? etc. First
phase. Does it tell you when it
happened? Which century BC? Okay. See,
look here. Look, it says it it tells you
it knows exactly when it happened. 14th
century BC. Why does it say 14th century
BC? Because the Arian invasion happened
in the 15th century BC 1500 BC is when
the Arians came to India. So obviously
this happened this battle happened 1
century later because the rigida as we
know was written in the 15th century BC.
If let's look at the riga what Wikipedia
says about Rigida when was it written?
Look 1500 to 10,000 BC. They have
decided they have decided it happened.
This this was written at 1500 or 1,000
BC. Let me let me show you more
distortions once again. Do we have any
reference to Sarasati here? Saras Okay.
Saraspati river. Now it'll let's see
what Wikipedia says about Sarasati. It
is a deified mythological river.
It's a deified mythological river. Okay.
And I mean let's see uh how does it how
does it claim it's defying its
mythological?
It will say that this is a mythological
river because the Arian because the
rigida refers to it. But the Arians who
wrote Rigida they wrote it in the 15th
century 1500 BC but this this river this
mythical river it dried up before that.
So how can they mention a river that is
mighty and all that? How can it be
possible? Circular reasoning. Okay. Now
coming back to the battle of the 10
kings. We have no idea when it happened.
The rigida
refers to the battle of the 10 kings
which means that it happened sometime
before the it was written or around the
time maybe the rigida was written over a
long period of time. So maybe it
happened after the first writings
happened or maybe before anybody wrote
any portion of the rigida.
Now the question then arises when was
the rigida written? That's the big
question. Wikipedia will tell you it was
written around 1500 BC because that is
when the Arian invasion happened. Before
that, how can anybody write it? There
were no Arians in India before 1500 BC.
What evidence do they have that it the
the Arian invasion happened in 1500 BC?
If if it even did happen, they have zero
evidence of it. Now they say, "Oh, no,
no, it was not an invasion. It was a
series of migrations." Well, show me
evidence of your series of migrations,
will none. So, this this is a brilliant
example of how Wikipedia distorts
history. There is no proof for the
claims that are that are mentioned as
set in stone in Wikipedia. Now, coming
to your question, in what period, what
time period of history did the this
battle of 10 kings happen?
So it is let's say it it happened
sometime around the time the riged veda
was written because it is mentioned in
the rigveda. Okay. So let's say
hypothetically it happened after they
started after our ancestors whenever
they were they started writing the
rigveda.
So then the question is when was the
riga written? Now the rigveda like I
mentioned it refers to the Saraswati. It
refers to the Saraswati as a great river
a mighty river a roaring river the
mother of floods.
Now we know the Saraspati existed. Now
nobody can deny that. Even though
Wikipedia still calls it a mythical
river, we don't care. It's it's it's
proven beyond any question of a doubt.
The Saraswati existed. It's this
gigantic paleo channel of a river that
go starts from the Himalayas and goes
all the way into the western Indian
Ocean, the so-called Arabian Sea, the
sea of Saashtra.
Right? So this great river existed and
you can see the paleo. You can see the
drainage channel. You want to see it?
I'll show you.
I I will show you. Okay, give me a
second. I'll I'll show you the I mean
the conclusive proof that a monstrously
massive river existed. Okay, we go to
satellite images. Here we go. Now, now
watch what happens. Okay, let's look at
forget about what you see overground.
Look at look at what's what you see
under the ocean. You see this in the
center of your screen? Do you see this
this channel in the ocean?
You can see this is an ancient drainage
channel of a major massive river under
the ocean. It still exists
and it probably was created when this
part of the ocean was above ground which
means it was it created it was created
maybe 10,000 or maybe several thousand
years ago and imagine how massive the
river must have been that it created
such a gigantic drainage channel right
so there you have I mean what else what
other proof do you need do you do you
see any other major channels over here
you can see one here which is the
channel of the Ganga
and it's it's kind of distorted because
it must have flowed in a different way
in the past several thousand years ago.
But this is one major drainage channel
the drainage channel of the Ganga and
here you have the drainage channel of
the Saraswati.
So this entire nonsense about the
Sarasati become a mythical river. These
people I don't know who they're trying
to fool and how long that they imagine
they can keep fooling people the the
Wikipedia idiots. Now when was the
Rigida written the rigida mentions the
Tarati great river massive river the
mother of floods the loudly roing river
and so on. So clearly the rigida the
people who wrote the the the rigida they
saw a massive river a river in her prime
not a river that is declining and drying
out. So when was the last time the
Saraswati was in her prime? around 6,000
BC
because it is known that the papers have
been published in nature that the Indian
rainy season the monsoon started
declining monotonically somewhere around
around 6,000 BC that's when the decline
started and that's how the Sarasi also
started slowly declining over several
thousand years over a period of several
thousand years the river declined
significantly eventually dried out
massively majorly
So it means that the rigida was written
closer to 6,000 BC when the river was in
her prime then to 1500 BC when she was
largely dried out in the southern part
of her course.
So it also indicates that the battle of
the 10 kings happened closer to 6,000 BC
than to 1500 BC. What is the exact time
period? We have no idea. When our
historians who are paid to do work when
they can devote their entire 15 hours a
day to that if when they start looking
into this we will know.
All right.
Next. Nirvana Shanks says given the
battle of 10 kings where King Sudas
defeated 10 more than 10 more than 10
united not tribes. We were not rag
ragtag tribals. We were clans.
These were not tribes. They Wikipedia
once again writes about rights of aran
tribe, Indo-arian tribes. These people
were not tribes people. They were not
tribals. What is the definition of
tribe? A tribe is a group of people who
live in isolation away from civilization
and they don't have any of the aspects
of civilization. That's a tribe. It's an
isolated group of people. 100, 200, 500
people living in isolation, living like
barbarians. That's a tribe.
The Rigidic people, they were grouped
into clans, not tribes.
But that's what your historians will
tell you. They were tribes. These were
Indo-Aran tribes. These were not tribes.
These were clans.
Uh clans and coalitions and
confederations. King Sudas was up
against a confederation, an alliance of
more than 10 clans who had all ganged up
to defeat him. Yeah. And he stood
against them and and he defeated them
all. And he praised Lord Indra for for
what happened because he was able to uh
breach a dam
and uh drown a lot of his his opponents
and that's how Bharat was united. Uh
yeah. So uh given the battle of 10 kings
where kings defeated a coalition of more
than 10 clans in the coalition war
against kinshi hang during the waring
states era in China. Are there more
examples in Indian or world history
where multiple powers united and were
yet were ultimately defeated by a single
strong ruler?
Yes. When what happened? I mean do we
have examples like this? The battle of
the 10 kings is like the the victory of
the underdog.
King Sudas against a coalition of more
than 10 clans numerically far superior
to him and yet through his military
strategy and acumen he's able to defeat
them. Incredible feat right? Are there
other examples? So one example is Kimshi
hang the the the Chinese the essentially
the uni unifier of China. The
unification of China happened what
around 200 something BC and he defeated
a bunch of other
a coalition of the Chu the Ki the Yan
the Shing Shang whatever Xiao Wei An all
these various groups they had formed an
alliance a confederation to fight him
but he defeated them and that's how he
was able to essentially unify the first
ever unification of China do we have
other examples of that well I can think
of a couple one example example is uh
well recent second world war Adolf
Fetler he was up against everybody I
mean he decided to fight everyone right
he decided to conquer the whole of
Europe he fought everyone he defeated
everybody uh of course he defeated them
one by one by one but especially when it
comes to the French and the British who
united in who formed an alliance he was
still able to defeat them and he was
able to conquer France so that's one
example
Napoleon
well before Hitler you had Napoleon a
guy with unlimited ambition and guy who
believed he could do anything and the
Napoleonic wars. So the Napoleonic wars
were kind of like that. Napoleon decided
to go and fight everybody everybody at
the same time. So when it comes to um
the battle of oustroliths some somewhere
in the beginning of the 19th century 180
something. So that is when Napoleon
fought against Britain, Austria and
Russia together. The three of them
united their forces to defeat to stop
Napoleon Bonapath. That's the battle of
Austerliths and Napoleon defeated the
three of them together the combined
coalition forces of Britain, Austria and
France u and and Russia. So and that was
essentially the the end of what they
called the the Holy Roman Empire. So
that's an example but it's not Napoleon
against 10 at the same time. It's
Napoleon against three at the same time.
So it's not as as great as what uh King
Sudas achieved. And then obviously you
another example is Chingish Khan.
Chingis Khan when when he was in his
teens and when he was growing up and
when he was in his 20s and 30s Mongolia
was a bunch of different tribes and they
all were fighting each other all the
time. And all of that was engineered by
the Chinese.
And eventually when Chisan became when
when he was still called Timujin and he
became a significant force in Mongolia.
Then there were then various tribes came
together and formed a coalition against
him and they had leaders like Jamuka,
one of his uh former friends and
eventual enemy. So they formed an
alliance against Teujin and Teujin
defeated this tribal co coalition, this
confederation. That was when he was
about 43, 44, 45, mid-40s. And that was
that that him defeating this coalition
was the formation of a unified Mongolia.
So whenever somebody has done this sort
of thing, it's it's created some kind of
unification. So King Sudas defeated this
alliance of 10 more than 10 clans. He
unified bat and that's the beginning of
the of of of
the I don't know the rigidic phase
perhaps of Indian civilization and
chingishan defed his this tribal
confederation that was the the formation
of Mongolia as the unified entity. So
you have some examples in history but I
can't think of any example that that
that kind of rivals what Sudas did one
against I don't know 11 12 essentially
not 10 more more than 10 so very hard to
find an example that is exactly similar
like you know up against that sort of
those sort of odds and still winning.
Okay, next anonymous scientist says the
US gained the USSR's support during the
Second World War because Hitler betrayed
the USSR with Operation Barbarosa.
What happened to the USSR relationship
after the war? Why did they start a new
rivalry or cold war? I mean, a great
question. They they used to be allies,
right? What happened? So the u the
Germans, the Nazis who obviously were
led by Hitler, they had essentially a
pact, a non-aggression pact with the
USSR of Joseph Stalin. It was called the
Molotov Ribthrop pact. This was a
non-aggression pact kind of not really
an alliance, but we won't fight each
other, you know, that sort of thing. And
uh that
was kind of the precursor, you know, it
it kind of it kind of made things easy
for Hitler for a while. So they had this
pact, the Molotov ribbon pact. And what
was it 194142 whenever it was operation
Barbar Rosa was launched? Hitler decided
now the pact is torn to pieces and I'm
going to invade the USSR. He did not
wait to finish the job with England.
Yeah. He decided, okay, forget about
England. let's go to the USSR. If he had
finished England off, which was
possible, then it would have been a
possibly a different story. And even
with operation Barbarosa, instead of
going straight for Moscow, he went for
the caucases where you had oil and gas
and he wanted that, but that allowed the
USSR to regroup. Anyway, that's a long
story. The point is that during the
Second World War, the Soviet Union after
Operation Barbarosa was on the
defensive. Initially, Operation
Barbarosa was a huge success. The
Germans made tremendous progress. They
essentially eventually reached the
outskirts of Moscow. They could see
Moscow through binoculars.
Yeah. But that's where
that's where grand old general of Russia
comes in, General Winter. And that's
when everything changed. But when the
USSR was on the back foot and they were
being hammered by the Nazis, they formed
an alliance with the United States. The
United States eventually did enter the
war after a period of dillydallying
and they were allies with the USSR and
they did provide a lot of uh support
material support etc to the USSR and uh
the objective was to defeat Adolf Hitler
right and uh then eventually the Soviets
start pushing forward surging forward
and most of the fighting and most of the
dying in the war was done by the USSR.
The USSR they lost about more than 20
maybe 27 million men in the war effort.
There must have been women al obviously
also but mostly I would say soldiers
right and in order to to win the war
they had to develop this massive
industrial complex massive industrial
complex. And the Soviets had an
advantage the Germans did not have. They
had inexhaustible
land all the way to the far east of
Asia. So they could afford to have
factories deep in their interior,
connect them with rail lines to the
front. And that's how they started
churning out the the the the weapons,
arms, ammunition, machinery, all of
that, aircraft, tanks, whatever that was
needed for the war effort. And that
created a massive industrial base for
the USSR. It in under Joseph Stalin the
USSR industrialized massively for the
war effort. And that's how they were
able to at immense cost the cost of
oceans of blood. They were able to
defeat Nazi Germany. The American
contribution is nothing compared to the
Soviet contribution in winning the war.
The Soviets also are accused of all
kinds of brutalities and atrocities.
Even the allies did the same thing.
Okay, let's not so let's not try and um
have somebody hold the moral high ground
because you watch some Hollywood movie.
Okay, that's not how the world works. Uh
so the US and the USSR were allies. The
moment the war ends, they become
enemies, right? The cold war starts.
Why? Because they were allies. It was a
it was an alliance of convenience. They
were temporary allies because they had a
common enemy. Once the common enemy was
defeated, now you look at each other and
you see something else.
The US looks at the USSR. They see that
this guy has enormous resources,
huge amount of territory, massive
industrial complex, massive military
complex, very powerful armed force,
hugely powerful military, thousands of
tanks, thousands of aircraft, millions
of soldiers and inexhaustible land and
resources. Otarchi,
well, there was only one other nation
like that which was the US. They had
acquired for themselves an entire
continent which they could rule. They
acquired it from the natives by killing
them. So they also had this but the USSR
had more resources, more material. So
clearly you can't be friends anymore.
That's how the world works. So they
became enemies and that's that's the
beginning of the rivalry which is called
the cold war cuz that's how that's how
it works in geopolitics,
right?
Aush Singh says, "How did the US and
USSR get their atomic bombs? Why do you
say that India is the only nation that
has an independent nuclear program?" I
have indeed said that and you are right.
You should ask the question, why do I
say that India is the only nation that
independently developed a nuclear
weapons program? Does it mean everybody
did it independently? Let's figure out.
So, let's begin with the US. How did the
US acquire its atomic bomb? It's called
the Manhattan Project.
So in the beginning of the 20th century,
you had a revolution in physics.
There were some
see at the at the end of the 19th
century, it was believed that physics
could predict everything. It could
answer everything. You want to know when
Hal's comet will come? Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
1910, then 1986. And then keep
calculating. You could know it. You want
to know what is the speed of of sound in
helium?
Well, you can the
you you can physics can tell you exactly
what the sound of sound speed of sound
in helium is to three decimal places. Uh
you want to understand electromagnetism.
Well, physics will tell you exactly.
Maxwell's equations will tell you every
everything you need to know about
electricity, magnetism and how they
interact and how they are how they are
the a single force. Essentially
everything you could imagine, you could
predict and explain through physics. But
then some cracks appeared in physics
and that was the black body pro problem,
the ultraviolet catastrophe and so on.
And then we discovered that you know
there's something called the atom.
There's something called the atom atoms.
Nobody believed in atoms until 1905 when
Einstein wrote his paper about the full
photoelectric effect. And eventually
long story short this gave rise to the
development of quantum mechanics and
then the discovery of radiation x-rays
18 1894 1895 whatever ro ron jun the
German dentist his wife's uh hand and so
on so then you discover radioactivity
radioactivity is a spontaneous decay of
atom of of certain atoms uranium and so
on and then physicists realize that you
do some stuff with radio radioactivity
it causes a chain reaction and
theoretically It can give you unlimited
energy but a runaway
form of energy. It's something you can't
control. And then very quickly they put
two and two together and said that if
you have sufficient quantity a
sufficient quantity of such file
material like uranium it'll just
spontaneously explode in a nuclear
explosion. But then such you needed you
needed highly purified uranium for that
more than 90% 95% purity for that.
That's called weapons grade uranium. So
how do you acquire that and blah blah
blah. So that's what the Manhattan
project was all about. J Robert
Oppenheimer was put at the head of the
uh head of the Manhattan project. It was
a highly secretive operation and it went
on for quite some time. They acquired
tremendous quantities of uranium ore
from Africa and they purified it and
they had to do a lot of you know physics
that had not been done before and
eventually they they tested the Trinity
explosion in Nevada or wherever it was.
There was the first explosion. So the US
atomic bomb was entirely indigenous.
They obviously they brought in the best
scientists from the world Enrio Fermy
and uh Feainman and Oppenheimer and so
many more so many more who all who all
worked together on the atomic uh bomb
project and that's how they were able to
test the bomb first in Nevada and then
in Hiroshima Nagasaki and so on we know
that
now when the Manhattan project was going
on it was a highly secretive operation
but there were spies there were spies in
the Manhattan project. Okay. Uh the
Rosenbergs and I I forget the names. You
can look it up. Okay. Espionage on the
Manhattan project. So once the Soviets
got to know that the Americans have they
also had excellent scientists, excellent
physicists, the Soviets. Okay. So the
Soviet Union had excellent physicists
and they came to know that the Americans
have already done this. So, so they
started developing their own uh atomic
weapons, nuclear weapons program and
they indulged in espionage. They had
spies who were working for them in the
US and the spies brought in a lot of
information, stolen information from the
US and that accelerated the Soviet
program. So the Soviet program was kind
of partially indigenous and partially
stolen from the US through espionage. So
the Soviets test their atomic bomb and
the Soviet Union becomes a second
nuclear weapons power and that gives
rise to the nuclear race, the arms race
and uh all that. Now then what happens?
The Soviets at that time had extremely
friendly relations with China. So they
helped China develop their atomic
weapons atomic energy and nuclear
weapons program. They gave a lot of
knowhow. They gave a lot of
technological technical assistance. The
Chinese had access to uranium which the
Soviets did not have. So the Soviets
wanted Chinese uranium in exchange for
so Chinese uranium. They gave knowhow to
the Chinese to make the Chinese nuclear
weapon. Some of the Chinese uranium came
from Axai Chin. Do you know why Axai
Chin is so important to China? Do you
understand why? And so on. So the
Soviets helped China develop the Chinese
nuclear bomb. So the Soviets got their
some certain nontrivial
percentage of information and knowhow
from the US and they passed a lot of
that on to the Chinese.
Now the British,
they also got some assistance from the
US. They helped the French. The French
also got some assistance from the US.
Maybe negative assistance, but they
still assistance. What is negative
assistance? What is negative help? It
means the Americans will tell the
French, we won't help you develop it,
but we will tell you what doesn't work.
So you'll not waste your time in the
wrong directions. That also helps. So
the British
nuclear weapons program and the French
nuclear weapons program was also
assisted by the Americans. The Israeli
nuclear weapons program,
it was strongly assisted by the French.
The French gave a lot of help to the
Israelis in developing their nuclear
weapons.
And the Israelis maybe got some uranium
from South Africa and so on. There was a
South African angle also in this. The
Pakistanis their nuclear weapons program
it's either Chinese or American. I think
their nuclear warheads are most likely
American nuclear warheads. So that
leaves leaves us with India. Did India
get any assistance from anybody? No. And
that's the end of the story. I I hope
that answers your question. And you can
look look all of this up. You can fact
check everything I said. Look it up. I I
invite you all I encourage you all to
fact check what I just said. Look it up.
All right. Next.
Krishna Ragunat of the Surinamese
Netherlands says, "I have done a little
research on the era in which Zaratustra
is supposed to have lived, but the
information contradicts itself." Well,
different claims contradict each other.
One claim says that Zaratustra lived 258
years before Alexander the Great. A
second explanation claims that Zoro
Zoroaster lived around 1500 BC which
exactly matches the rig with the date of
Max Miller. A third explanation claims
that Zeratustra lived 5,000 years before
the Trojan War. What's my view on this?
So because the Greeks destroyed all
Persian records, that's why we don't
quite know when Zeratustra lived.
Um,
so what's the truth? this 1500 BC Max
Miller, let's throw it out of the room
right away, okay? Uh we don't need to
waste our time talking about Max Miller
and his dates. Uh his dates were based
on God knows what theological
calculations that according to the Adam
and Eve theory, the theory of creation,
the world was created in so and so date.
So, so Indian culture and civilization
cannot be older than that obviously
then. Yeah, that sort of thing. So, um
Genesis, that's that thing. So let's
forget about what what Max Mueller said
in his 1500 BC arian arian invasion
nonsense and rigida was written 1500 BC
forget about that um
zeros one claim says zeratustra lived 28
years before Alexander so Alexander
invaded India and Persia which year
which year
it was
uh it's right before it was when the
Nanda dynasty was in power in in India
and few years before the morian dynupta
with the assistance of vishoptanaka. So
let's quickly google this because I
don't remember the exact date because
you should never memorize dates. You can
always refer to them. So let's go to
google uh date of Alexander's date of
Alexander's
u disastrous
invasion of India.
Okay. when 327 326 BC okay that's when
he invaded so uh if Zaratusra lived 258
years before that that's 527 BC plus 577
585 BC 585 BC is what that that claim
would give us now a minus
A
minus
okay when did he lived 7th century BC
well That kind of makes sense. It's
possible. It's it's plausible. I would
say plausible. If it is 585 or 580 or
something BC, it would be after aish.
So the founder of the Aminid dynasty was
this gentleman Akinus or Akamanish or
Akamanish.
And he was definitely not a Zorastrian.
He if he was not a Zoroastrian, well
what religion did he follow? Well,
obviously the Vic religion, right? What
else? Um, so it's I think that is a
little plausible that he that Zarathra
lived maybe a century or two after the
founder of the Akid dynasty. That kind
of could make sense. Um,
Zarathra. So if you if you look at the
name Zaratustra, it's two words Zarat
and Ustra. Zarat means yellow or golden
and Ustra means camel
in Sanskrit. So it means golden camel or
yellow camel. Maybe he had a golden
camel or maybe he was the owner of
yellow camels. I don't know what it was
but that sort of thing. That's the kind
of name it is. Um 5,000 years before the
Trojan War. Well, when did the Trojan
War happen? Tro Troy has been
discovered. It's it's currently present
day in in present day Turkey. It's a
place called Hisarik. So that is most
likely the site of historical Troy which
at that time Turkey used to be Greece.
uh and that battle if it happened the
the the war of Troy the Trojan war it
would be around maybe between 1500 BC
and 2,000 BC around that time. So if
Zeratus lived 5,000 years before that
there would be 7,000 BC which I think is
a little
it's like farfetched a little bit. Yeah.
So I would be
I I I would be more inclined to say that
he must have lived a few cent maybe two
and a half centuries before Alexander's
attempted invasion of India. Maybe that
makes more sense. But nobody has the the
the conclusive answer as to when
Zaratustra actually lived because yeah
we don't have the answer because all the
records are gone. The Greeks destroyed
all Persian records. So we don't know
the answer but most likely after the
foundation of the Akimeirate dynasty.
Okay. Shahasara
Shahasara says why did the British
construct famines all over India? How
would they benefit from these famines?
Would that not cost them in the long
term by decrease in tax collection and
loss of manpower for their informal
slavery? Why would why? It's a good
question. Why if the British are
occupying India, why would they have
people die off in the millions, why not
keep them alive and and have more tax?
Right? So, understand this. We know what
happened in 1857,
war of independence. And the British had
a great had a very hard time, you know,
surviving that. And before 185 1857,
there was more opposition to the
British. Our land was under foreign
occupation. It was a brutal occupation
and we fought our people fought the
British. Now what's the best way to
prevent a people from fighting? You
starve them.
You starve them. If they don't have food
to eat, how will they fight?
India was the home of 330 million
people.
It's okay to kill a few million every
every year. It'll it'll keep them in
check. If they're all skeletonized and
starving, how will they fight us? We can
still tax them.
That's why the British starved Indians,
that's how the British engineered
famines in India. Now the question also
arises, how did the British engineer
famines in India? How did they do it? I
mean, how do you engineer a famine? So,
so the British were very systematic in
engineering famines. They had
very exploitative economic policies,
very exploitative agricultural policies.
They obviously prioritize their
interests, their commercial interests,
their imperial interests. Uh they how
how do you start a famine? You force
farmers to stop planting food crops. You
force them to plant cash crops. You make
them plant opium which you will then
sell to China and extract silver and
gold out of China
through opium
taken out of India which was which was
which you obtained by forcing farmers to
to grow opium instead of food crops. So
you're forcing farmers to grow opium.
You're forcing them to grow grow indigo.
You're forcing them to grow cotton. But
who is going to grow the food grains?
Right? So that's one way of of
constructing a famine of of of
engineering a famine. Then when a famine
happens, you you are the government in
some parts of India. So you will do
famine relief measures. What kind of
famine relief measures you'll do? You
will say okay you people are starving.
I'll give you solution. You guys come
and do hard labor for me ext.
So that is famine relief. Right? Um and
the British had extremely exploitative
land revenue and taxation. They had
something called permanent settlement.
They had something called the horrific
riyatvari system. Right? They they stole
all the lands all the land of the
Indians. Today Indians don't have land.
Right? Why do Indians don't have not
have land today? Indians don't have land
today. Most Indians have no land.
Before the British came, most Indians
had land. Before the Turks it came, even
more Indians, everybody had land. Today
most Indians don't have land. and they
go to cities and they live in rent and
whatn not. What happened to the land of
the Indians? The British government took
it and then it was passed on to the into
the Indian government and Zabindari
system all kinds of horrific things. The
Rayataware system it stole the land of
the people. It imposed and the British
imposed extremely high exorbitant
land taxes taxes. They forced farmers to
do subsistance farming and that too of
cash crops instead of food crops in
order to not be killed so that they can
pay their taxes to the government. High
taxes, theft of land,
forcing people to grow cash crops, no
food security. When we had Indian kings,
there was food security. the Indian
kings is to maintain huge reserves of
grains because every few years there's
the elino kind of situation and maybe
two three maybe one or two years there's
the monsoon fails but if you have
sufficient reserves of grains you can
distribute them and you can wave off the
taxes for that year that's what the
Indian kings would do that's why India
never had famines even if you go back to
rakari and birana and all that like
5,000 7,000 BC you see these huge grain
silos in which grain could be stored in
tons
So India always had this system. The
British destroyed all of that. H
then whenever there is a famine the
British would export the grains to
Britain and to other British colonies.
So and then you would have some grain
but the the farmers would have to buy it
from the British at extremely high rates
and because the farmers are are taxed so
heavily their purchasing power is next
to nothing. Right? And whenever you had
famine relief relief camps, they would
give less food than the Nazis gave to
Jewish prisoners in their concentration
camps.
So there was increased mortality in
these famine relief camps. And the
epidemics, the death toll, nobody
counts, right? And the British, you know
what people what the British lovers tell
us? The British gave us railways.
They constructed the railways for us.
Without the British, we would not have
the railways. The railways were the
infrastructure of extraction.
If you had a railway network across
India, then maybe if there's a famine in
some part of India, you could transport
the grains and whatnot there. But the
railway system was constructed for
extraction which is from the places
where you have mines and and resources
the British want to the ports like
Mumbai, Kolkata, wherever. The railways
were only used for extraction. They were
never used for famine relief, food
movement, nothing. So everything
collapses right and in India another
thing Indian kings, emperors, queens,
whoever they invested in irrigation. You
would have ponds in every village. You
would have canals everywhere. You would
have dams. Right? The British invested
in railways and they killed off all the
irrigation.
Right? So that caused more vulnerability
to drought and so on. I can just go on
and on. how the British engineered, they
constructed, they designed, engineered
and implemented famines all across
India. The objective and whether Indians
died or lived, they would get what they
want. They did not want taxes from
India. They wanted resources from India.
They wanted labor from Indians and they
got it anyway. India was a land of
plenty. If a few million Indians die,
there are so many more Indians to work
for the British. So one year you can
have a famine in Odisha, Odisha. one
woman one year you can have in Tamil
Nadu one year you can have in Gujarat
next year you can have in maybe three
other parts of India you keep on moving
the famines around and ensure that
people are just oppressed all the time
that's what the British did very very
very very systematic policy extremely
intelligently executed the British
probably the most evil thing the British
have ever done done anywhere
all right
Norman Auda says If the Greeks were
originally of Indian descent, why didn't
they worship the gods using their real
names? And if they were Indians, then
how and why they changed their language
from Sanskrit to Greek. So this idea
that the Greeks were of Indian origin
comes from various sources. Let's put
one of the sources. One of the ideas is
that you know you had the battle of the
10 kings. Okay. Now and and those 10,
11, 12 clans were expelled from India
forever and they became the originators
of the Indo-Uropean languages across
Eurasia. Oh. Uh, Talagiri
10 kings. Uh, I uh clan names.
Clan names. Okay.
Was Vishwa Mitra etc. Let's see. The
Dash in the battle of the 10 kings and
Lina. Okay. So, who are the opponents of
Kings Sudas? The Pritus, the Parthas,
the Parththeians, the Pershus and the
Pashas, the Persians. There we have it.
You can see already the Shimus, the
Brigus, the Druhus, the Alenas, the
Paktas, the Pakti, the Pashons, the
Balanas, the Bolanas, the Shivas, the
Visharins
uh uh and so on. So he ex he tells you
who these people were, the Simu, the
etc.
Nuristani, Pishanin, the Pakun, Pakta,
the Bulani, Bhalana, Parthoparthians,
Paro, Persians,
Madra, the Maday, the Mids, the Ka,
Alina, Smatians. So when it comes to
Greece,
the Alina
clan that faced off against uh which was
one of the 11 or 12 clans that faced
that faced kings, the Alina, they
probably are the originators of the
Helenic people. The Hellenic people are
the Greek people obviously, right? So
that is a strong possibility. It is not
proven for sure, but it's a strong
possibility. Now, if this battle
happened around 6,000 BC and Pers and
Greece became a high civilization 2,000
BC, that's 4,000 years, that's a gap of
4,000 years. A lot happens in 4,000
years and it explains a lot if this
theory is true.
Now, tell me something.
You It's a great question that you're
asking. Now, let's understand it
logically. The question you're asking is
why didn't the Greeks if they were
originally of Indian descent? Why didn't
they worship the gods using the real
names?
Now tell me today h today in India how
many of you worship Lord Indra
using any name? How many of you worship
Dorsetru?
How many of you do? Has anybody even
heard of Dors Petru? The pitu
the father of Indra
that was the original god.
The pitu and pritim mata the sky father
and the earth mother those were the
original gods and go go goddesses god
and goddess
nobody worships them today in India.
Who worships Lord Indra today? Nobody
does.
What happened? We ourselves have
changed.
Who worships scand today? Some people in
south India some people. But the rest of
India, does anybody remember scand?
We had an emperor named after scandupta.
One of our great emperors,
right? We have forgotten so many of our
own gods.
We have relegated them to obscurity.
Right?
And we have so many new names for gods
and goddesses. I mean we have multiple
names for gods and goddesses that
evolution happens in India also. And if
they if the if the question is why did
the Greeks change their language from
from Sanskrit to Greek? Well simple
question how many of you speak Sanskrit
today in India? How many how many do
people speak Bengali, Asamis, Kashmiri,
Punjabi, Marathi, uh, Odia, Gujarati,
Oranavi,
you can go on. What happened to
Sanskrit? Why don't Indians speak
Sanskrit today? The same process that
happened in in India happened everywhere
else. And that's the answer. Very
simple. All right.
All right.
Swapnil Mishra says once upon a time
there was an ambitious plan called
Atlantanropa to fully drain the
Mediterranean Sea and reclaim land to
connect Europe and Africa. So why is
that even today a comparatively smaller
project like building a bridge between
Spain and Morocco has never been
realized.
Interesting question that combines world
history with kind of present day stuff.
But okay, let's go to the map. What was
this plan at Tropa like? Let's go. Let's
go to the map.
So around the 1920s,
there was a German engineer whose name
escapes me now. You can look it up.
There was a German engineer who proposed
creating a gigantic hydroelect electric
dam in the straight of Gibralar.
And this project would entail
essentially draining much of the
Mediterranean Sea, which is this this
sea here. And it would bring the sea
level down by about 10020 meters which
is a massive change which would
completely completely transform the
landscape of this entire region. It
would essentially connect Africa and
Europe and it would free up a lot of
land for settlement and resource
extraction and whatnot. So that plan was
called Atlantropa. It was a hugely
ambitious plan and completely unfeasible
because of the engineering challenges
involved. So that's why nobody took it
seriously. It was a very ambitious plan
but the engineering challenges were
immense. It's almost like terraforming a
new planet almost like that and the cost
would have been exorbitant astronomical
hundreds of trillions of dollars perhaps
that sort of thing. So that's why it was
never taken seriously.
But if you just take a small portion of
that and say that okay we just create a
land bridge.
Okay. To create a bridge, not just a
land bridge, maybe a tunnel, maybe a
bridge or maybe a tunnel across the
straight of Gibralar. So we have the
nation of Morocco here on the south and
we have the nation of Spain in the north
and between them there's this little
straight of Gibralar. What's the width
of the straight?
It's about 15 kilometers. That's it.
Just 15 kilometers. Why can't this be
done? For example, one example you can
give is the the the channel tunnel
between France and the UK. So we have
the English channel over here. And
what's the distance? Let's measure the
distance. It's about 35 or something
kilometers and there is this underground
tunnel that goes under the straight
under the British channel under the
straight of do essentially and uh you
can uh essentially travel by train from
London to Paris in I don't know very
short period of time an hour or two I
suppose because the the French TGV
trains are extremely fast
TGV anyway so if the British if this
channel tunnel can be constructed under
the under the ocean then why can't you
construct
a bridge or or or a or a tunnel between
the across the street of Gibralar which
is even the distance is even shorter
it's less than half of uh the width of
the other project that's the question
now why is it that this hasn't happened
there's still proposals that we should
do this I mean they should do this so
why hasn't it happened is the question
I'll tell you Okay. First of all, when
it comes to the British channel, the the
the the depth of the sea between France
and England is on average 50 60 70 m.
Okay. So, the bottom of the sea is about
50 60 70 m more or less roughly
approximately on average on average
maybe around 60 m. That's the depth of
the of the English channel. But when it
comes to the straight of Gibralar,
the depth must be I don't know 600 700
800 m maybe a kilometer. So it's
tremendously deep. Tremendously deep.
Imagine
constructing a bridge in a place where
in in a part of the ocean which has a
depth of a kilometer. I mean it's a
whole different kind of challenge,
right? It's nothing compared to what
they did uh with the channel tunnel.
Nothing comparable. Totally different
engineering challenge. And secondly,
this place, the straight of Gibralar, it
is right at the boundary of the Eurasian
tectonic plate and the African tectonic
plate.
That's a tectonically active region.
What does it mean? The plates keep
moving moving. It's about half a cime
per year the movement. Very small,
right? In 10 years it's 5 cm. If you
have a bridge
and there's a shift of 5 cm it will
collapse the bridge. Just 5 cm is enough
to collapse a bridge. If you have a
tunnel under the ocean and the wall
moves one portion of the wall moves by 5
cm it's going to be a catastrophe.
You don't want to build anything
sensitive in that region. So because of
these reasons, yeah, that's why this
project has never happened.
Amisha Mishra says, "What exactly was
Athenian
Athenian democracy? Was it truly as
radically democratic as popularly
imagined? Was it unique or or did other
Greek states, city states also had this
this also have this sort of thing,
democracy?" Right? So people the whole
world will teach you your your Indian
history textbooks will teach you your
Indian professors and teachers will
teach you in school that Greece is the
motherland. It's the it's the birthplace
of democracy. Athens was the ideal city
state. Democracy came from Athens. What
do you people know you backward Indians?
What do you people know? Democracy is
the cornerstone of the civilized world.
And it emerged in Greece in Athens.
Athens was the was the shining light in
the world of darkness. Athens gave us
democracy.
Athens had direct democratic governance.
In the fifth century BC, 4th century BC.
See, how long ago? 2 and a half thousand
years ago, you had democracy in Athens.
Political power was exercised by
citizens. They had it was exercised by
citizens through elected
representatives.
What the hell? I mean, no, they did not
have elected representatives. They had
direct governance
by citizens. Now what's the truth my
friends? What is the truth? Rick
democracy.
Let's examine the truth and please I
invite you all to fact check what I am
saying.
Okay? Please fact check what I'm saying.
Look it up. Go to Google. Go to whatever
it is that you go to these days. Look it
up. So when it comes to Athens, yeah,
there was democracy.
Citizens could vote. Who were citizens?
Only citizens could participate in the
democracy. Right? Only citizens. So what
is the definition of a citizen of
Athens?
The definition of a citizen in Athens
was a free adult male
who Yeah. Free adult male.
What does it mean to be a free adult
male? Male. Male. First of all, you have
to be male. So 50% population gone.
women could not participate in this
democracy. 50% out of the window. But
when it comes to the other 50% who are
males, we're talking about free adult
males. So children gone,
maybe 20 30% gone there. So we are left
with what? I don't know what percentage
we left with. So it means that about 10
to 20% maybe 15% of Athens population
could actually participate in this
democracy and vote the eligibility
eligibility was adult male male citizens
and also yeah there was another another
piece of eligibility free adult male
citizens who had completed military
training. If you had not completed
military training you could not
participate in the democracy. Now what
does it mean by free? Why not just adult
males? Why not? What does it mean to be?
What does this criterion mean free? It
means you must not be a slave. Slaves
are very bad. Slaves cannot vote. No,
no, no, no, no. What is the percentage
of slaves in Athens?
15 to 30%.
Yeah. So, Athens may have a may have had
a population of maybe two 250,000 2 and
a half lakhs out of which maybe you had
one lakh slaves.
H
oh no. So you had about one lakh slaves
out of a total population of 2 and a
half lakhs. So only one and a half lakhs
are not slaves. Then out of those remove
the women, remove the children, remove
the males who have not completed
military training, you're left with 10
15%
of the population of Athens who could
participate in this so-called democracy.
You see, slavery,
slavery was an integral part of the
structure of the civilization.
It was an integral part of the social
and economic
way of life in Athens. And Athens was
was had a great reputation for having
the largest slave populations of any
Greek city state.
And the slaves were not people who were
who were were maybe abducted from Africa
or something. There were Greeks. Greeks
who were who had been enslaved. Yes.
Okay. Very good. I think that should
answer your question. And the other city
states also had similar things. But
Athens was the was the great democratic
place. the the greatest of the
democracies in the city states. Other
city states aspired to be as great as
Athens. So they also tried to emulate
Athens and they also had their own forms
of similar democracies. But there you
have it. Is that what you call
democracy? Really? H really?
Okay. Next the question.
geopolitical dubes were ancient Indian
and Egyptian kings and people in direct
contact or was it just trade contact
through indirectly through Mesopotamia
see in those days we did not have
aircraft so if I feel like okay to to
let's let's go to Cairo and visit the
pyramid so I go and book my things and
you know 3 days later I'm in Cairo
doesn't did not work like that you had
to go to Egypt it was like a journey of
a lifetime you would go by ship
You would cross the western Indian
Ocean, Indian Ocean. You would go into
uh let's go to the map right very
quickly. Where is map? Here is map. So
if you had to go to Egypt, you would
cross the western Indian Ocean. You
would go into the Gulf of Aen. You would
go through the straight of the of Babal
Mandib. You would then go up the Red Sea
northwards and then you would end up in
Egypt, which was this region. That's
what you would do. So only traders would
do that. Kings did not visit each other.
In those days there was no state visit.
Like right now Mr. Modi, our prime
minister, he was in Japan yesterday, I
believe, or day before today and right
now he's in China. So world leaders
today, they go on state visits and they
visit each other and they know each
other very well. Those days leaders,
kings, emperors never visited each other
unless they visited their wasals. That's
a different story. It is possible that
um it is likely that Chandra Gupta Mori
our emperor would have met with Salucas
Niketta the the emperor of the Seucid
Empire. That's possible because that was
a very unique set of circumstances. That
is quite possible
but in ordinary conditions you would
never have a king meeting with another
king especially from other parts of the
world would not happen. Um so ancient
Indian and Egyptian kings kings would
not meet and and for example like like I
said when kings met their vasals and
carried out correspondence. Let me show
you a great example from Egypt. Okay the
Amarna letters let us go to our friend
Google. Some people tell me why don't
you use perplexity or something. Now I
will use Google. So uh it's called Amar
Amarna letters right? Yeah there we have
it. So this uh the Amarna letters we'll
go to Wikipedia. I showed you very very
clearly how Wikipedia distorts Indian
history but we can look at this. Okay.
Uh
Amarna letters. So this is this is
diplomatic correspondence between uh the
kings of Egypt and their various
neighbors. This is very interesting.
Akinatan and Tosharata
Sharata was the king of the Mitani and
he had extensive correspondence with
with Akinatan. After akinatan dies, he
has correspondence with Akinatan's widow
and then he has correspondence with the
next king as well. Very interesting uh
correspondence that you see over here.
Mitani King Tisharata Amen Hutep II. So
Toshirata's sister was married to the
Pharaoh of Egypt. Then his daughter was
also married to the Pharaoh of Egypt. So
you have this extensive correspondence
and it's about golden statues and all
and Tosharata is complaining a lot uh he
has a a letter to the widow of the king
also. So when you find this sort of
thing it's it's really interesting and
this still survives for Egypt but we
kind of have lost uh all records of our
history written records unfortunately.
So the coming back to the main question,
this was actually a digression that I
did here because it's interesting.
Always fun to think of something
different. Yeah. But yeah, so there was
trade contract between India and Egypt.
You would have traders traveling to the
two civilizations. You would have
Egyptian traders coming to India. You
would have Indian traders going in great
numbers to Egypt. That sort of thing.
It's very clear that around 2000 BC you
had the presence of Indians in Egypt
because you have the introgression of
Indian cattle in Egypt. The zebu cattle
that only live that only originated in
India nowhere else.
And was it indirectly through
Mesopotamia? I would imagine it would
have been direct contact not through
Mesopotamia through a proxy. Why do you
need a proxy? You trade with me
Mesopotamia. You can also trade with
Egypt directly. So it would have been
direct trade.
Kithan Desai says after the 7th century
when the Arabs and Turks invaded India
from the northwest many kingdoms fought
them and stopped them from advancing
towards India but history books give
very little information about this
period please tell us about this era and
suggest a good book related to this era
okay when it comes to books I don't know
of any book nobody in India no historian
has bothered to write a book about this
era because then the truth will come out
and then Indians will stop fighting each
You see today what's happened is this
between the 7th century when Muhammad
bin Kasim in tries to invade Sind and
then until and then about what when does
Babar and all those all these
individuals come to India that's many
centuries later when Baba came to India
India was still not under complete Turk
occupation even north India was not
completely under Turk occupation you
still had a lot of resistance
so let's quickly Google This I I I
forget dates. Okay. So Google it. When
did
Baba invade India?
Uh 1505.
So 7th century. When did Bin Kasim
When did Bin Kasim invade India? Uh 711
AD. 711 AD to 1505. How many? That's 800
years.
800 years India was still
largely free.
Why was India still largely free despite
all the repeated invasions and attempts
to expand the the Delhi Sun and all?
Because Indians fought, Indian kings
fought. But this entire period of
history is whitewashed away from Indian
history textbooks. Why? Because they
want Indians to keep fighting each
other.
Who was it that fought the invaders at
the time? It was the people we call the
Rajputs. They fought, they bled, they
died. You have no idea how many of them
died. The women had to commit horrific
ends to themselves. They have to even
destroy their bodies while dying. You
know, Johar
that sort of thing. Horrific period of
Indian history. Incredible bravery,
incredible valor, incredible sacrifices.
But no historian writes about this. So
that today you have all these you know
today if you go to social media you will
find Indians fighting each other. It's
always Baratas versus Rajput or somebody
else versus this or this versus that or
that always it's always someone trying
to portray that me and my people were
better and you people were losers and
the other guys say you were losers and
that sort of thing they the objective is
to keep Indians fighting each other.
Everybody contributed to to to fighting
for India at different points in time.
711 AD is when bin Kasim tries to invade
India and then there is this repeated
wave after wave of invasions first by
the Arabs then by the Turks. Continues
continues for centuries. Eight centuries
go. The Moguls then arrive in India.
Babar and they they establish a small
foothold in India and then it takes
another couple of centuries until orb
kind of you know creates this huge
kingdom which in includes much of India
8 centuries who fought. If nobody fought
then how did the Turks not not conquer
the whole of India by that time? It was
the Rajputs who fought. The Rajputs
their their resistance was tremendous.
Their bravery and their sacrifice was
tremendous. But history books will give
you very little information about this
so that Indians can keep fighting each
other. Indians don't know the
contributions of those who fought for
India. That's the point. My point is not
to say that so and so is great and so
and so is not great or whatever.
Everybody fought for India different
points in time after the Rajput flame
was extinguished that happened when the
the the Turk Empire became large and all
the Rajputs were vitalized eventually
that's when the Maratas took over and
the Maratas defeated and destroyed the
Turk Empire but because of infighting
the British were able to overcome them.
Long story that's how it goes. Uh is
there any good book about that this
period of history the first inv the
first 800 years of invasions? I don't
think so. I don't know of any. No Indian
historian has bothered to write about
this.
There we have it.
Judge Navalia says if hypothetically the
indigenous people of Americas of the
Americas did have immunity to old world
infectious diseases like small pox etc.
as much as the European colonizers had.
Would the situation in the Americas be
such that most people in the Americas
today would be native genetically but
mostly religiously Christian as is the
situation in subsaharan Africa and papa
New Guinea today? Ah interesting
question interesting this is a
hypothetical question but it's an
interesting question. So once again we
go back to the conquest of the Americas
by the Spaniards. Brutal barbaric
invasion of the Americas. First you have
the Spanish conquest of the of the
triple alliance. The triple alliance is
in the Yucatan region, Mexico.
Tenokitlan was their capital city. It is
now called Mexico City. This is around
1519, 1520, 1521. And the perpetrator of
the atrocities and barbarities was Heran
Cortez. Hernan Cortez. He was this
Spanish concistador
who conquered the Triple Alliance with
the help of natives of of locals. So the
Spaniards come by ships, small number of
Spaniards and they try they want to
invade this kingdom and this kingdom is
actually an empire. It's a it's an
alliance of three states together and
they obviously have a bunch of vasals
because an empire has vasals. Now
whenever you have vasals, was unhappy,
right? They want to be free. So when a
foreigner comes and say, "Oh, somebody
has come from like god knows how many
fire how many miles away, thousands of
miles away. let's take their help and
overthrow our overlords and then we'll
be free then we'll get rid of the
Spaniards. That's what they thought. So
they allied with the Spaniards. The
Spaniards marched onto Tanuktitlan the
city with tens of thousands maybe
hundreds of thousands of allies who were
natives and at that same time there was
this massive smallpox epidemic that was
raging because of the Spanish presence
in Mexico. It was the presence of it was
the combination of two forces. First,
the small pox epidemic and secondly the
alliance of the Spanish with tens of
thousands maybe hundreds of thousands of
natives that led to the decline and fall
to the defeat of the triple alliance.
And then the Spaniards killed off the
their allies also and they had no
intention of going back and they
colonized and Christianized everything.
They destroyed all the temples. They
burned all the books. They they killed
the emperor. They did all kinds of
horrific atrocities. Even today, the
natives remember that. And yeah, they
Christianized Mexico in the region.
That's what happened. And then you have
the conquest of the Inca Empire, which
is western South America.
Okay. Peru. No, what? Peru, Chile, that
region, right? So that is a maybe a
decade or so after the defeat the
destruction of the triple alliance. So
the conquest of the Inca Empire was done
by another barbarian called Franchesco
Pidaro. Okay 1530s early 1530s we're
talking about and uh the Inca Emperor
was Atawalpa
and he was killed by the the Spaniards
and similarly once again you had small
pox and other horrific epidemics the
Spaniards bought. So that is kind of how
things happened. Now with that explained
in tremendous detail, let me address the
question. If hypothetically these
indigenous people had immunity to these
diseases, then what would have happened?
Then they would have defeated the
Spaniards
and then Christianiz Christianization
would not have happened. Even in North
America,
whether it's the French or the or the
English, wherever they appeared, natives
started dying out.
because
of uh the epidemics brought in the the
the diseases they brought in. Um even
the Spaniards who who explored Florida
etc. they also wherever they passed you
come back 20 years later there's no
villages left. It was a thriving place
tens of thousands of people suddenly
nothing left. There's no villages
nothing. So wherever these people went
the Europeans diseases spread
and that's how so many of the natives
they died and the resistance was futile.
They could not resist the the invaders
and that's uh how things went and the
invaders were not content with occupying
the land and oppressing and subjugating
the natives. They also destroyed their
culture and imposed Christianity on the
natives.
Uh so if this immunity existed
then most of the people in the Americas
would not just be native genetically but
they would also not be Christian. That's
how I see it. Now comparing with
subsaharan Africa.
Subsaharan Africa was decimated by two
foreign religions. One was Islam. Second
was Christianity. So Africa if you look
at it today there's very little
indigenous religion left today. Most of
it is either Islamic or Christian. But
Africa is different from the Americas
because Africa was much closer in
proximity geographically to Europe and
to the Islamic world. So it was very
easy to invade. But when it comes to the
Americas, they across a gigantic ocean,
the Atlantic Ocean, very hard to invade.
So that's why I I I I I would say that
if this immunity had existed, the people
would be genetically native and also
they would still have their original
culture and religion. They would not
have been Christianized. That's how I
think it would have gone. But it's
obviously a hypothetical question
because we know what's what's happened
there.
Shahas Sara says, "How did Shri Ching
Khan know so much about war strategies,
tactics, leaderships and other knowledge
required to conquer and rule such an
empire while growing up in a small tribe
in Mongol wilderness?" Okay, good
question. That's a question I may not
have addressed before. How did he know
all these things? He was the ruler of
the of the largest empire ever, right?
He conquered half of the known world of
his time. How did he know so much about
war strategies, tactics, leadership,
administration,
communication? How did he know all these
things? Okay, here's the deal.
Jungaskhan was born, he was name, his
name was Tujin, birth name. He was born
in a small tribe called the Bourjigan,
the Borgjugan tribe, which is the blue
wolves. His father was the was the
chieftain of the small tribe. His name
was Yasui. So his father dies when
Teujin is about 8 or 9 years old and the
tribe expels Teujin's family out of the
tribe because some other guy because see
once the father dies the son the eldest
son must become the the next chieftain
of the tribe but the butug's children
were all kids so one of his lieutenants
wanted to become the the chieftain but
for that you have to get rid of the
family. Now you can't kill the family of
the of the previous king kind of. So you
just abandon them in the wilderness and
in Mongolia if you are abandoned in the
wilderness it is guaranteed death
because in Mongolia in winter the
temperature goes to minus30° there's no
food there's nothing so Timujin and his
family were abandoned like that they
were left to die but somehow they
survived somehow through tremendous
hardship they survived and Tuojin
becomes well a young man and uh he
spends his teens his 20s his 30s
fighting. He starts creating his own
tribe. He starts fighting the other
tribes. And he lost many battles as a
young man. He lost many battles. He had
a lot of betrayals, lot of hardship, lot
of heartbreak. He lost a lot. But he
somehow survived. When you fight,
sometimes you win, sometimes you lose.
But if you have this, you will learn.
You'll learn how to what tactics work.
what tactics failed because I lost that
battle. Why did I lose the battle? You
analyze the the defeat. Then you realize
what went wrong. Then you next time you
don't do that. You do something else.
You use a different set of tactics.
That's how you learn strategy. That's
how you learn how to handle people.
That's called leadership.
Then once you have a small number of
people under you, you could you learn
how to administer the whole thing. And
once you start defeating more tribes and
bringing them into your fold, your
understanding of administration and
leadership grows. So Chingish Khan
finally Teujin finally unified Mongolia
at the age of about 44, 45, 46,
right? So he had about 30 plus years to
learn all of this the hard way. He
learned on the job.
Nobody came and sat down with him beta,
let me teach you strategy, let me teach
you tactics, let me teach you
leadership. No, he learned it the hard
way. The very hard way. And that's why
he was really good at it. Right.
Amisha says, "Why is Julius Caesar so
important? What makes him stand out in
front of other Roman emperors or
figures?"
Oh, well,
Julius Caesar.
Yeah. Well, he was a pivotal figure. Why
was it why was he a pivotal figure?
Okay, let's go back to history to to the
history of Rome. See Rome, the history
of Rome has multiple phases, multiple
periods.
One period is the Roman kingdom
which was established in the 8th century
BC or something. Okay, so Rome used to
be a kingdom, a small kingdom and they
had many see in Italy Rome was is just a
small region. Let's go to the map. Let
me show you. Let us go to Rome.
Let us go to Rome.
All right. So we're talking about Rome
which is Italy.
So Rome is the city here and the kingdom
of Rome was a small kingdom over here
and they had many other neighbors of
other kingdoms the Sabine kingdom and
what whatever the names were they had a
lot of kingdoms around them and that was
the kingdom period of Rome. So Rome was
a kingdom then Rome became a republic a
ganatantra or ganarajia
a republic. So in a republic you have uh
essentially some participative form of
government not exactly democracy when
you have half the huge slave population
and women can't vote and all it's not
like that but you had a senate so Rome
had a senate and and rich wealthy people
could be elected to the senate and rich
wealthy people could vote in the
elections that sort of thing males only
males
so you had some very prominent wealthy
families whose people would be in the
Senate and the Senate would decide the
affairs of Rome, how things would go and
all and so on. So that was the period of
the republic. The period of the Roman
Republic was an extremely turbulent
period. It was a period of expansion,
slow expansion initially, but they
fought a lot of wars. It was a per
period that was characterized by
constant warfare essentially. They the
three Punic wars with Carthage
eventually Carthage was defeated.
Hannibal and all the other kingdoms in
Italy, they were all destroyed,
defeated, subjugated and absorbed.
um and so on. So this was the the
republican period of Rome in which the
Senate had a tremendous amount of power.
It was not power was not concentrated in
one place. It was the Senate which had
the power which is a whole bunch of
people old guys wearing to okay that
sort of thing. Then Julius Caesar
emerges and he's a soldier and uh what
Caesar did is that he was the bridge
between the the republican period and
the imperial period. He put an end to
the republic essentially through his
actions. How
when Julius Caesar
emerged on the scene, he was a soldier
and and so on. He came from a well
recent decently wealthy family, a
noblyish kind of family. And
once he became a soldier and a general,
he launched the greatest conquests Rome
had ever seen. First of all, he crossed
the Alps and he went and conquered Gaul,
which is present day France.
Then he was not content with that. So he
went and conquered Iberia which is it
which is which is Spain. Not enough.
That's not enough. So he went and
conquered England. He conquered the
British islands. Not the whole of the
thing but his conquest of of Britain of
some parts of Britain was the beginning
of the Roman occupation of of the
British islands. Then he's not happy
enough with that. So he goes and
conquers Greece. That's not enough. So
he goes and conquers Egypt. Wherever he
goes he conquers. So suddenly the Roman
dominion expanded from this to
huge huge huge huge
and then when you conquer so much you
will not be content be with being a mere
senator right so Julius Caesar appointed
himself dictator officially dictator
okay not not he became a strong guy
that's why we call him a dictator no his
title was dictator of Rome
and then he had this the alliance with
Cleopatra, the Greek uh queen of Egypt
and they had a son. So that's when the
Senate become really really worried that
now we're going to have a king. We have
Julius Scissor who is who is in alliance
with a queen and they have produced an
offspring a male child and they are now
going going to rule us and that's what
eventually got him assassinated
but that was the end of the republic
because after that two of the people who
were the closest associates of Julius
Caesar Mark Anthony and Octavian
Octavian was Julius Caesar's adoptive
son and Mark Anthony was very closely
associated with Julius Caesar his
rightand man perhaps perhaps an adoptive
son also. I'm not sure. Octavian was the
here was the was the was the adop
adoptive adoptive son. So Octaven and
Mark Anthony they go to war and the
winner of the war becomes the first
emperor of Rome. No more so-called
democracy, no more Senate. The Senate
continued to exist but it was just well
performative.
It was just mostly ceremonial. the once
Octavian became Augustus Caesar all the
power in Rome was concentrated in the
hands of one person. So Julius Caesar
was the transition from the republican
period to the imperial period and he
made it inevitable that Rome will have
an emperor even though he himself should
have been that but the but that could
not happen because he was assassinated
but his adoptive son became the first
emperor. Augustus Octavian became
Augustus.
So Caesar by by the dent of his enormous
conquests made it impossible for Rome to
remain a republic. He conquered more
land than anybody else in the history of
Rome. So essentially so that's why
Caesar is so important. That's why the
people still remember Caesar. That's why
we have titles like Kaiser. The Kaiser
was the you know you had emperors in in
Europe who were called Kaiser. It means
Caesar. What does tar mean? The Russian
word sar it means Caesar. What does
Kaiser a hind mean? It means Caesar of
Hind and so on. That's why he is so
important. I mean a pivotal personality
in the history of of Europe in Rome.
Feminist Slayer says, "Can you explain
Cleopatra's relationships with Julius
Caesar and Mark Anthony including the
children from the these unions and how
these alliances impacted Egyptian and
Roman politics?" H interesting question.
Cleopatra. Cleopatra was a Greek
princess.
She was um she belonged to the to the
tomic dynasty. So Egypt used to be under
Persian occupation. Okay. Persia had
conquered Egypt. And then Alexander
comes this way and he says, "Let me go
and conquer Egypt." But he finds that
the Egyptians are welcoming him. Please
sir, please come liberate us from the
Persians. So Alexander says, "Okay, no
fighting required." He just comes and
takes over Egypt. Essentially very
little fighting required and he
installed a governor in Egypt Alexander
whose name was Tlemi. After Alexander
died, Tlemi became the king of Egypt and
that was the beginning of the Tmic
dynasty. Ashok called him Tulamaya.
There was a successor of the original
Toll Tamaya. So uh Ashok is in our
emperor Ashok. Um so you have the tomic
dynasty which is a Greek dynasty in
Egypt and Cleopatra belonged was a child
of this dynasty and she was the queen of
Egypt but Cleopatra had political
problems
in Egypt all the well going back to the
day times times of the pharaohs
um all the power was was concentrated in
the hands of siblings. The Egyptians
used to practice sibling marriage and
all you know whatever. Anyway, so so
Cleopatra had political problems. Her
two brothers and sisters also wanted
power. She had two brothers and she had
a sister and they all coveted the power.
They all wanted to be the the sole ruler
of Egypt. So she faced that problem and
and her ministers and counselors some of
them they also played this game of
political intrigue. So Cleopatra wanted
to consolidate her position as the only
sole queen of Egypt and nobody but there
should be no political problems. There
should be no challengers.
So to do that she allied herself with
Julius Caesar who had already
essentially invaded and conquered Egypt.
So she allied herself with him and this
union produced a child Cesarian.
Okay. And that created problems in Rome.
So Cleopatra if I'm not mistaken she
visited Rome and that frightened the the
Roman senators because they saw that
this guy the conqueror of half the world
from their perspective it was half the
world Julius Caesar who has conquered
everything gold Iberia Britain uh Greece
Egypt such a powerful guy the whole the
entire military worships him now he is
an alliance of the Egyptian queen and
they have a child so now they're going
to rule us and we will have a king we'll
have to bow down at his feet and that's
why they assassinated Julius Caesar
So there was a there was a big problem
for Cleopatra. So then Cleopatra later
allied herself with Mark Anthony
and uh Julius did not regard his son his
son Cesarian as his legitimate heir for
whatever reason. But Mark Anthony had
two or three children with Cleopatra. I
think three children.
How many girls? How many boys? At least
one girl. At least one boy. I don't
remember who was a third. But Mark
Anthony had three kids with Cleopatra.
And Cleopatra allied with Mark Anthony
and the objective was to consolidate her
position, her political position in
Egypt. And then what happens is that we
have the war between Mark Anthony and
Octavian. And Octaven wins. Mark Anthony
meets his end at his own hands. And
later Cleopatra also well not at her own
hands but at the fangs of an asp which
is an Egyptian serpent.
Um and what happened to her children I
think one of her children one of her
daughters was married to King Juba I of
Moritania which was a North African
kingdom and they yeah and some other
kids were married somewhere else that
sort of thing. So that was a deal. So
did the alliance impact Egyptian
politics Roman politics to some extent.
to some extent but not to a great
extent. Egypt had lost sovereignty
because of the conquest of Julius
Caesar. So it was a vasal. It was a
nation under occupation and Egypt did
not ever go up again. It went it only
went down after that.
Okay. Next question. This is by Nirvana
Shanks. Which single technological
innovation before 1500 CE had the
biggest immediate impact worldwide?
So when you talk about technological
innovations, you would think maybe it's
something like a nuclear technology,
nuclear weapons or aircraft or military
tech technology something like that. I
would say it is the printing press by
Johannes Gutenberg somewhere in the
1400s.
Why was it so important? Why did did it
have such a big impact?
We know that India was the civilization
that invented education, which invented
the the univers university system. We
had universities all over the place. But
we never had a printing press. Because
of that, all the manuscripts in our
university libraries were handwritten.
They were painstakingly written by hand.
Imagine how much effort went into
writing a million manuscripts.
Right? Because of that knowledge was
concentrated in small centers of
education.
It was not widespread.
But the Europeans once they invented the
printing press they started printing
everything. First was it was the Bible
and whatnot. But eventually technical
literature became available in print.
And that's how ideas that the Arabs had
taken from India and transmitted to
Europe, they spread so fast in Europe.
And that is what contributed to the very
rapid industrialization and scientific
progress and technological progress in
Europe because these ideas were they
were able to transmit so fast. You could
just print could just print books, mass
produce them and send it wherever you
needed. Before that you had to write
everything down and even making a copy
would take months. Now we could
mass-produce books and all this
dangerous knowledge, technological
knowledge, it spread like wildfire and
that is what contributed to the
Europeans ruling the world for the past
500 years and that still continues. So I
would say it is the printing press by
Johannes Gutenberg which was probably
the most impactful technological
innovation before 1500.
Okay.
Uh, Nitish Kumar Sharma says, "I think
I've asked it before. Let me try again."
Okay. I have been thinking a lot lately
about this and would love to know your
opinion. What who do you think had a
bigger impact on human history, Lord
Buddha or Lord Jesus Christ? Without
falling into the euroentric worldview
and simply based on historical facts, I
know it touches religion with which is
complex and personal matter. But without
getting into the sensitive part of it,
what do you think? Okay. Who was more
impactful? Was it
Lord Buddha,
Sedartha Gotham? Or was it Mr. Jesus
Christ? Okay, let's not get get into the
whether so and so existed or not and all
that. Let's say we had these two
historical figures. Who was more
impactful? So Buddhism both the dharma
which is part of of of our dharmic
umbrella, it became very prominent in
the subcontinent for a few centuries.
Almost everybody we all had Buddhist
ancestors. We all have
Buddhist ancestors who lived about 2,000
plus years ago. Our ancestors about
around that time were Buddhists. Then
once again you had a reversion to other
forms of dharma and which we call
Hinduism today.
So and Buddhism was very easy to spread
because it was simpler. It was not as
philosophically
challenging challenging conceptually
challenging as as the other forms of of
dharma. So who was it? Alan Watts who
said I think it was that uh Buddhism is
Hinduism stripped down for export. So it
was very easily exported out of India
and the whole of Southeast Asia at one
point in time was even first Hindu and
then Buddhist.
So China was Buddhist, Japan was
Buddhist, Mongolia was Buddhist, the
whole of Southeast Asia, Thailand,
Burma, everything was Buddhist at one
point in time. So very impactful for
sure. It spread it spread through
people-to-people contacts, trade
contacts and so on. That's how it
spread. It had a vector property, a
property that causes the spreading of
the idea.
But it was through human contact,
people-to-people contact that the spread
happened. When it comes to Christianity,
today you have more Christians than
Hindus or Buddhists or Hindus and
Buddhists put together. So if you want,
what is the metric we're looking at?
What is the metric of impact? Is it the
number of people affected? I mean I mean
touched if that's the metric of impact
Christianity has had a bigger impact
because more people in today in today's
world are Christian than Hindu plus
Buddhist put together. Uh so
Christianity had a different vector
quality. It also was happy to spread by
the sword by destroying uh cultures that
existed by destroying them and replacing
those cultures with with Christianity.
Read that book the the darkening age by
Katherine Nixie and you will see how
Christianity spread in Europe by
violently destroying existing cultures
and religions and super superimposing
itself on the people over there. So
Christianity had a different kind of
vector quality. It was it would it would
spread not just by people-to-people
contact and trade contracts but through
violence. So it was more successful that
way.
So overall I would say
Christianity has been more impactful
which would mean that Lord Jesus Christ
Jesus Christ was more impactful. If you
look at it from today's perspective if
you look at the impact today Jesus
Christ has been more impactful than Lord
Buddha. We are not going into who right
who's wrong who's better who's worse.
Impact how many people affected
there we have it.
Okay, we have crossed two hours. So, I
will not take more questions. I will
take questions from the live chat for
the next 10 or so minutes. All right.
Uh, Vladimir Putin says, "I have read
the book. It's so horrible." Yeah. Well,
yeah. I'm glad you have read it then.
All right.
Okay. Let's let's take some questions.
If you have questions that you would
like to ask me right now in the live
chat, do ask me now and I'll take a few
questions.
Okay.
YouTube P says pay who came up with the
idea of the crusades and how did the
conflict develop up to the ra rise of
Saladin also who are the key kings of
Jerusalem before glo
and why did the war continue okay that's
a very interesting specific set of
questions okay first of all the the
broader question is who came up with the
idea of the crusades must have been the
Vatican
I don't know if any specific individual
who decided Okay, we need to tell all
the kings of Europe to go to Jerusalem
and liberate Jerusalem. I don't know if
who specifically would have come up with
this, but it came from the church. The
church was the driving force. So I would
say it came from the Vatican. It came
from Rome. But who specifically? I'm not
sure. We we can look it up. But yeah, so
it came from the Vatican. And then the
Vatican was the overlord of Europe. Not
just the spiritual overlord of Europe.
It was the actual imperial force, the
imperial power. All the kings in Europe
were essentially vasals of the Vatican
of Rome of the Roman
church.
Um and u and you just you did not merely
have crusades for the so-called holy
land which is the reclaiming of
Jerusalem. You had the northern crusades
which was crusades against against
Europeans which was to spread Christian.
I mean there are still Europeans who
practice indigenous culture, the
indigenous religion,
polytheism, how dare they destroy them.
So you had the northern crusades. It was
King Charleman of of the Franks Francia
or present day France who launched the
northern crusades and and converted a
lot of Europeans to Christianity by
force by through brutal methods. But
that's the northern crusades. You had
two waves of crusades in in Utam, which
is uh which is today's Israel region.
One was around one around 1,000 AD or
something around that time. Please don't
ask for the dates. You can look it up.
It was I think there were and there was
one set of crusades
uh and around the time of Saladin and
and Richard the Lionhe Heart.
Uh so it was it's it's because the the
Islamic world had conquered Jerusalem
and and what the Europeans considered to
be the holy land where Lord Jesus Christ
was was apparently born. So that's why
they wanted to liberate this region and
that's why the crusades happened. Who
were the key kings of key kings of
Jerusalem before Gus and how the why did
the war continue? I don't remember the
names of the kings. I I'll have to go
back and delve into history. Don't
remember. We had the Guzino and you had
various other people. I don't remember
the names right now. Okay. So that's
what I can tell you. All right. Next.
Uh
okay.
Hi Penguin says, "What's the history and
significance of Burma and what was its
relation with today's civil war of
Myanmar?" History and significance of
Burma. Well, that's a very ancient
story. They were been around for
hundreds thousands of years. Bhadesh. It
was used to be a part of Surabumi
essentially. Surabumi is what we call
what used to be what is today Thailand.
But Dharma was well
uh history they they've had very
powerful kings and empires. You have the
Tongo kingdom which which uh with which
Manipur had lots of conflicts over the
years and so on. It's a it's a very very
broad in broad question that you're
asking history very long history been
around for a very long time
and they've had very powerful kingdoms
there they came into conflict with
Manipur like I said they had conflict
conflicts with other kingdoms also in
the region and initially they were Hindu
they later they became Buddhist and
today also they are Buddhist and then
Burma came under British occupation
around the same time that Manipur saw it
sovereignty being eroded by the British
And then Burma Burma became part of
British India. In 1935 the Burmese voted
to stay with India but the British
forcibly separated Burma from India
despite the vote for remaining with
India be remaining unified with India
and after the British left they left
behind a military government and uh it
was kind of isolated and that's why it
was easy for other countries to play
games there. India never wanted to be
the big brother the the the provider of
a security umbrella for Burma and that's
why the the Chinese got involved in that
and today the civil war that that's
happening there is kind of a proxy war
between the US and China in Burma in
in uh in the north northeast part of
Burma you have tremendous deposits of
rare earths
on the border with Yunan Chinese
occupied Yunan and the Chinese they they
they seek that they they they take that
they buy it from the Burmese and the
Americans want that they want those rare
earths and that's kind of the deal
right
okay what else do we have what else do
we have
anonymous scientist says why are Hebrew
and some other languages so different
from the Indo-Uropean lang language
family probably because the history is
different because
See the Indo-Uropean language family it
originated in one place somewhere most
likely India the Europeans will hate
this when I say it but yeah Hebrew is
not Indo-Uropean burner I saw you Hebrew
is not Induropean it's a Semitic
language it belongs to the Semitic
language family
and when you have different language
families it means that their ancestors
evolved separately from the other
language families. So in the old days 20
30,000 years before today the world's
population was very sparse human beings
very sparse some people there was no
communication there was no trains or
aircraft so people if they lived in one
part of the world they would live there
for 10 20 3000 thousand years in
isolation from everybody else so that's
how language families developed and
that's why Hebrew is different because
it's part of the semitic
language family
Um,
Polomi says Pali is just one of the
prairits. Oh yeah, it is one of the
upper branch languages which is the
prairits. Pali that is correct.
Um,
Ladir Putin says Samodra Gupta or
Napoleon will both existed both both
were significant but Samudra Gupta
was the the the unifier of India and
Napoleon was the destroyer of Europe. So
difference
difference there. Um
all right what else do we have
what else do we have? Um
I spoke about Rajut struggles of Rajut
it'll take hours. So yeah I have this
question by Aush Singh. Tell us about
the struggles of Rajut. It's a very very
long history and story and full of
tragedy uh that that I can't explain in
the next two three minutes. It's it's a
very big topic but good question. Okay,
I I'll take it this take it up hopefully
some other time. Hi Penguin says is the
okay hy penguin a lot. Is the influence
of the Kushan Empire on today's India
far greater than the influence or the
influence of Roman Empire on today's
Europe? I would say Rome on today's
Europe. India whether it is the Kushan
Empire or the Gupta Empire the influence
is very less in India today because we
have been completely westernized our
entire system is western it's a colonial
system the influence of whether it's the
Kushan Empire or the Marata Empire or
the Chola Empire or the Gupta Empire is
minimal today minimal because we have
completely colonized ourselves
Ah
look itachi space if I knew this this
the answer to this question
who are the real power holders behind
the curtains could highlight their
characteristics
these things are supposed to remain
secret right I I don't know really oh we
have some super chats really okay we
will take the super chats don't don't
take any more super chats I don't have
the time Rahul says do you think
American experiment is failing. Do you
would you agree that such an
artificially created entity that makes
no attempt to create a civilization
connect in its population can ever
succeed?
Artificial entities are imperial
entities. They're not civilizational
entities. America is not a civilization.
America is an empire. Is it failing? No.
It's not doing as great as before, but
it's still there. It can still rule the
world for another 200 years if it gets
things right. So, I don't think it's
failing, but it's it's definitely
declining. I mean living standards are
declining the the the the quality of
society is declining right there is
visible decline in in in the United
States so there is decline but it
doesn't guarantee failure if they still
get things right they can still rule
uh Harshai says have you watched Tashkan
files Kashmir files I haven't seen any
of those so I'm sorry I I've not seen I
don't know I haven't seen those I don't
have have the time to watch movies I'm
sure they're great movies I'm sure many
people have spoken spoken about this but
I haven't seen these. Uh now he's
bringing Bengal fights also. My thoughts
on these types of movies. I think uh we
need to have movies like these movies
that bring out the truth about what's
really happened and it obviously will
make a lot of people unhappy but you
know it's a free country so they should
come out. Ram Bodh says king who lost
his kingdom built an army from the
jungle fought and gained back his
kingdom.
Who's this this king and what's the
story? King who lost his kingdom built
an army from the jungle fought and
didn't go gained back his kingdom that
is Vanraj Chowa obviously I mean that's
one example Vanraj Chaa
uh Zuts says two-part question Q1 are
there similarities between the old Greek
and Hindu gods single source Q2 what
baffles me is how the Greeks converted
to Christianity so quickly without
violence why can the same happen in
India there was violence there was
violence
it looks like it there wasn't any
violence Whereas the Greeks obviously
did not want to give up their culture
and religion. It was all forced out of
them. It was done brutally, violently.
Read that book, The Darkening Age by
Katherine Nixie. You'll understand that
Christianity was imposed on all the
polytheistic cultures of Europe through
brutality, through force. Are there
similarities between the old Greek and
Hindu gods? Okay, let me give you an
example. Zeus. Zeus, right? Zeus is the
god of thunder.
Thunder.
Zeus
fights Typhen, a great sea monster, the
sea monster Typhen.
He has enveloped the entire world's
oceans and he is with withholding the
water from the world. So the world is
under drought and Zeus the great god
with his thunderbolt comes and defeats
Typhen and frees the waters of the
world. He he liberates the world's
waters and that's how the world
survives. Zeus
That is Indra.
That is also Thor,
right? That is Indra. Indra is the god
of Vajra. Vajra is a hammer. It's also a
thunderbolt. He defeated Vitra, the
great Assura, the great sea monster who
who imprisoned the world's oceans and
Indra defeated him and he's the god of
the thunderbolt and the vajra and the
hammer. That is Zeus. Zeus Peter.
What is Zeus Peter? It is Dors Petro.
Similarities, there are tremendous
similarities. This is this is just one
example.
Godliness says historically republic
India has faced the most brutal war in
1962 with China. Please explain the
details and mistakes of the Indian
political leadership and military
leadership of the time.
The leadership
neglected and marginalized the army. If
you want to have a strong country, you
need to have a very powerful military.
You need to give them give the military
everything it wants. Give them all the
arms, all the ammunition they need. Give
them a tremendously powerful air force
excellent fighter planes. Give them
clothing that is that is suitable for
high altitude combat. Give them
snowshoes. Give them goggles. Give them
everything. The Indian army was a rag
deck army at the time. It was starved of
everything it needed. Secondly, when the
Chinese built a road through Oxai, Mr.
did not know it for a few years and then
we when he came to know he said but not
a blade of grass grows there who cares
about axin it's your territory
there so many such such issues and then
there was political issues and so much
more so
yeah and first of all why were was China
allowed to invade and occupy Tibet Mr.
Neu supplied the Chinese soldiers rice,
Indian rice, they were starving. Without
that, they would not even have conquered
Tibet. So, so many so many problems. And
this is the last question for today.
Godliness says Sarasati Hindu
civilization was roughly 3,300 BC. And
many Indian historians believe there was
also the time of Mahabharat. That was
also the time of Mahabharat. What's my
perspective on this?
The Saraswati Sindu civilization that
period of history starts around well the
oldest archaeological site from this
period of time is Birana
7,500 BC that's 9 and a half thousand
years before today. So that is the
initial phase of the Saraspati Hindu
civilization that period of our history
3000 BC or so that's the mature phase
that's when the civilization was at its
peak peak fully industrialized fully
urbanized extremely high prosperity
living standards all that that's 3,000
BC 3,300 BC but the beginnings are
an an example of the beginnings is
Birana that is 7,500 BC when it was very
rural sort of
So that that's the deal first of all and
secondly time time of Mahabharat I have
no idea I am not getting into that fight
that controversy what was the year of
the Mahabharat which year did it happen
uh clearly the Mahabharat if you look if
you read the text it is it depicts a
much more developed India compared to
the Ramayan the Ramayan it kind of
depicts a more
more rural kind of India you do not have
huge cities and all that during the time
of the Ramayan Mahabharat yeah so it
kind
is consistent with uh the the kind of
industrialization and and urbanization
you had during the Saraspati Hindu
period. So Mahabharat could be from that
time period and the Rigveda it is a
completely pastoral India completely
rural India. Ramayan more developed
Mahabharat extensively developed. So it
is possible that the Mahabharat could be
contemporaneous with the time of the
Saraswati Hindu period of our history.
All right, people. That brings me to the
end of today's live stream. Good fun.
Always great fun talking to you all.
Great fun. Thank you so much for all the
questions. And tomorrow we're going to
have a geopolitics episode. So, I look
forward to seeing you all there in case
you're interested in geopolitics. Thank
you so much. Take care. Keep asking
questions. Keep learning. Keep raising
your standards. And I will see you
tomorrow. Good night. Bye-bye.